<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2011, v.4002-->
<!DOCTYPE reference PUBLIC "-//IBM//DTD DITA IBM Reference//EN"
 "ibm-reference.dtd">
<reference id="l0wskc02_cvbbmap" xml:lang="en-us" rev="sh20i1">
<title>DES control-vector-base bit maps</title>
<titlealts>
<navtitle>Control-vector-base bit maps</navtitle>
<?Pub Caret -1?>
<searchtitle><keyword conref="wskc_conref-l0wskc04.dita#conref-l0wskc04/cca_long"/> (<keyword
conref="wskc_conref-l0wskc04.dita#conref-l0wskc04/cca"/>): Control-vector-base bit
maps</searchtitle>
</titlealts>
<shortdesc>Details of the control vector base bit maps.</shortdesc>
<prolog>
<metadata>
<keywords>
<indexterm>Control-vector-base bit maps</indexterm>
</keywords>
</metadata>
</prolog>
<refbody>
<section>
<p>Four figures below provide a bit map summary of valid control vectors by DES key type:</p>
<ol>
<li><xref href="#l0wskc02_cvbbmap/wskc_cv_base_bit_map_1_of_4" format="dita"/> shows the CV bits
common to all DES control vectors.</li>
<li><xref href="#l0wskc02_cvbbmap/wskc_cv_base_bit_map_2_of_4" format="dita"/> provides CV bit maps
for key types that are used for encipher and decipher data operations.</li>
<li><xref href="#l0wskc02_cvbbmap/wskc_cv_base_bit_map_3_of_4" format="dita"/> provides CV bit maps
for key types that are used for the remaining data operations (such as MAC generate and MAC verify),
and PIN processing.</li>
<li><xref href="#l0wskc02_cvbbmap/wskc_cv_base_bit_map_4_of_4" format="dita"/> provides CV bit maps
for key types that are used for cryptographic variable encrypting, key encrypting, and key
generating.</li>
</ol>
<p>At the top of each figure is this header, which deserves additional explanation:</p>
<fig expanse="column" id="wskc_cv_base_bit_map_hdr">
<title>DES control vector header</title>
<image href="wskc_cv_base_bit_map_hdr.jpg" placement="break" width="500">
<alt>Control vector base bit map (data operation keys)</alt>
</image>
</fig>
<p>A control vector (either the base or, for a double-length key, the extension) has 8 bytes.
Observe that the header shown above has eight columns, one for each byte of a control vector.</p>
<p>A control vector has 64 bits, numbered from left to right starting with bit 00 (the most
significant CV bit) to bit 63 (the least significant CV bit). The first byte has bits 0 – 7
(indicated in the header as &lt;00..07>, while the last byte has bits 56 – 63 (indicated in the
header as &lt;56..63>.</p>
<p>Each of the eight columns in the header has eight dots (periods), one for each control vector bit
of the byte. Over each even-numbered control vector bit is a two-digit number (00, 02, 04, and 06
for the first byte and 56, 58, 60, and 62 for the last byte), the first digit stacked over the
second. This provides an easy way to identify each bit by number.</p>
<p>
<fig expanse="column" id="wskc_cv_base_bit_map_1_of_4">
<title>Bit map of DES control vector base and extension (Part 1 of 4)</title>
<image href="wskc_cv_base_bit_map_1_of_4.jpg" placement="break" width="500">
<alt>Bit map of DES control vector base and extension (Part 1 of 4)</alt>
</image>
</fig>
</p>
<p>Here is an explanation of the bits common to all DES control vectors:</p>
<ul>
<li>CV bits 4 and 5 (marked with a 'u' in the figures) are undefined by CCA. These bits are
available to be defined by any non-CCA user-defined extension (UDX).</li>
<li>CV bits 7, 15, 23, 31, 39, 47, 55, and 63 (marked with a 'P' in the figures) are parity bits.
Each byte of a control vector must have even parity, and it is an error if any of those bytes does
not have even parity. Conversely, each byte of a DES key normally has odd parity. When CCA encrypts
a DES key, it first exclusive-ORs the key-encrypting key with the control vector to form the actual
key used in the DES key-encrypting process. The key resulting from this exclusive-OR has the same
parity as the key-encrypting key.</li>
<li>CV bit 17 (marked with an 'E' in the figures) is used to control whether a key can be exported
or not. If a DES key-token has CV bit 17 = B'1' (XPORT-OK), the key can potentially be exported (see
CV bit 57). If CV bit 17 = B'0' (NO-XPORT), the key cannot be exported. The <keyword
conref="wskc_conref-l0wskc04.dita#conref-l0wskc04/vbnmpex"/>, <keyword
conref="wskc_conref-l0wskc04.dita#conref-l0wskc04/vbnmpee"/>, and <keyword
conref="wskc_conref-l0wskc04.dita#conref-l0wskc04/vbnmrkatr"/> verbs can be used to change the
control vector so that the key in the token cannot be exported (that is, to set CV bit 17 =
B'0').</li>
<li>CV bits 30 and 38 are anti-variant bits. These bits guarantee cryptographic separation between
non-CCA variants and CCA control vectors, which may unavoidably be mixed in some implementations
internal to a node. CV bit 30 must be B'0', and CV bit 38 must be B'1', otherwise the control vector
is not valid.</li>
<li>CV bits 40 – 42 (marked with "fff" or "FFF" in the figures) are key form bits. The bit pattern
of these three contiguous bits determines the length of the DES key and whether the key parts are
guaranteed unique (ignoring key parity bits). See <xref href="wskc_r_kformbfff.dita"/> for more
information about key form bits.</li>
<li>CV bit 56 (marked with a 'W' in the figures) is used to control whether a DES key cannot be
wrapped using the weaker legacy method. If CV bit 56 = B'1' (ENH-ONLY), the key must be wrapped
using the stronger enhanced method. The only exception to this rule is when a single-length key,
which is always wrapped using the legacy method, is in a fixed-length DES key-token with the
ENH-ONLY bit on.</li>
<li>CV bit 57 (marked with a 'T' in the figures) is a TR-31 export-control bit used to control
whether a DES key can be exported by the <keyword
conref="wskc_conref-l0wskc04.dita#conref-l0wskc04/vbnmkext31"/> verb into a non-CCA TR-31 key block.
If CV bit 57 = B'0' (T31XPTOK) and CV bit 17 = B'1' (XPORT-OK), an export of the key into a TR-31
key block is OK (allowed) provided that CV bit 17 = B'1' (XPORT-OK). If either CV bit 57 = B'1'
(NOT31XPT), CV bit 17 = B'0' (NO-XPORT), or both, the <keyword
conref="wskc_conref-l0wskc04.dita#conref-l0wskc04/vbnmkext31"/> verb is blocked from exporting the
DES key. Note that if CV bit 17 = B'0' (NO-XPORT), the key cannot be exported by any verb.</li>
<li>CV bit 61 (marked with a 'u' in the figures) is used to identify whether a control vector can be
used by CCA. If CV bit 61 = B'1' (NOT-CCA), the control vector cannot be used by CCA, otherwise the
control vector can be used, provided that is is otherwise valid.</li>
</ul>
<p>
<fig expanse="column" id="wskc_cv_base_bit_map_2_of_4">
<title>Bit map of DES control vector base and extension (Part 2 of 4)</title>
<image href="wskc_cv_base_bit_map_2_of_4.jpg" placement="break" width="500">
<alt>Bit map of DES control vector base and extension (Part 2 of 4)</alt>
</image>
</fig>
<fig expanse="column" id="wskc_cv_base_bit_map_3_of_4">
<title>Bit map of DES control vector base and extension (Part 3 of 4)</title>
<image href="wskc_cv_base_bit_map_3_of_4.jpg" placement="break" width="500">
<alt>Bit map of DES control vector base and extension (Part 3 of 4)</alt>
</image>
</fig>
<fig expanse="column" id="wskc_cv_base_bit_map_4_of_4">
<title>Bit map of DES control vector base and extension (Part 4 of 4)</title>
<image href="wskc_cv_base_bit_map_4_of_4.jpg" placement="break" width="500">
<alt>Bit map of DES control vector base and extension (Part 4 of 4)</alt>
</image>
</fig>
</p>
<note>When CV bit 40 = B'1', the left and right keys are guaranteed to have unique key values
(ignoring parity bits). In other words, these key types are not allowed to have replicated key
halves. A double-length Triple-DES key with replicated key halves has an effective key length of
single.</note>
</section>
</refbody>
</reference>
<?Pub *0000001699?>
